<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Golden bull: or, The fundamentall lavves and constitutions of the Empire Shewing, the persons and priuiledges of the princes electors, the manner of the election, the forme and ceremonies thereof, with other politique orders to be obserued by the states and subiects of the Empire, which shall bee assembed at Francford (for the election of the now next emperour) the tenth day of Iuly next ensuing. 1619.</title>
            <title>Bulla Aurea. English</title>
            <author>Holy Roman Empire.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1619</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 92 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03490</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13611</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104148</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839887</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839887</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4347</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03490)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4347)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 963:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Golden bull: or, The fundamentall lavves and constitutions of the Empire Shewing, the persons and priuiledges of the princes electors, the manner of the election, the forme and ceremonies thereof, with other politique orders to be obserued by the states and subiects of the Empire, which shall bee assembed at Francford (for the election of the now next emperour) the tenth day of Iuly next ensuing. 1619.</title>
                  <title>Bulla Aurea. English</title>
                  <author>Holy Roman Empire.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[60] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T[homas] S[nodham] for Nathanaell Newbery, and are to be sold at the signe of the Star vnder S. Peters Church in Cornehill, and in Popes-head Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1619.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of the Bulla Aurea of the Holy Roman Empire.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Cf. Folger catalogue, which gives signatures: A-G⁴ H² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Constitutional history --  Holy Roman Empire.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4347:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4347:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE GOLDEN BVLL: <hi>OR,</hi> The Fundamentall Lavves and Conſtitutions of the <hi>Empire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Shewing,</hi> The Perſons and Priuiledges of the <hi>Princes Electors, the manner of the</hi> Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, the forme and Ceremonies thereof, with <hi>other politique Orders to be obſerued by the States</hi> and Subiects of the Empire, which ſhall be aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled <hi>at</hi> Francford (<hi>for the Election of the now</hi> next Emperour) the tenth day of <hi>Iuly next enſuing.</hi> 1619.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Imprinted by <hi>T. S.</hi> for <hi>Nathanaell Newbery,</hi> and are to be ſold at the ſigne of the Star vnder S. <hi>Peters</hi> Church in Cornehill, and in Popes-head Alley. 1619.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="proclamations">
            <pb facs="tcp:4347:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4347:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Imperiall Lawes and</hi> Constitutions, ſet downe in the Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den <hi>Bull, or Letters Patents of CHARLES</hi> the fourth, Emperour of <hi>Rome,</hi> for <hi>the Election of Emperors.</hi> (<g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g>)</head>
            <div type="proclamation">
               <opener>In the Name of the most holy, inſeparable and glorious Trinity. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>HARLES the fourth, by the Diuine grace of God, Emperour of <hi>Rome, ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Auguſtus,</hi> and King of <hi>Bohemia;</hi> for a perpetuall memorie to all Poſteritie, Sendeth greeting. <hi>Euery kingdome diuided in it ſelfe, ſhal be madde eſolate; for the Princes thereof are become fellowes with theeues:</hi> therefore the Lord ſendeth the ſpirit of Blindeneſſe amongſt them, that at noone day they grope about as if they were in darkenes; and remoueth their Candleſticke out of their place, that they ſhould be blind leaders of the blinde, and they that walke in darkeneſſe offend, and are decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and being blinde, commit wickedneſſe, and
<pb facs="tcp:4347:3"/> fall into diuiſion. Tell mee <hi>Pride,</hi> how didſt thou raigne in <hi>Lucifer,</hi> but by the meanes and aide of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſention? Say enuious <hi>Sathan,</hi> how didſt thou caſt <hi>Adam</hi> out of Paradiſe terreſtriall, but by making him to diſobey God? Speake <hi>Luſt,</hi> how didſt thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy <hi>Troy,</hi> but by cauſing <hi>Helena</hi> to forſake her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band? Say <hi>Wrath,</hi> how didſt thou deſtroy the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth of <hi>Rome,</hi> but by mouiug <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi> and <hi>Pompey</hi> to ciuill and inteſtine warre? Thou <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie,</hi> like a craftie Serpent, creeping into the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Empire (which by the power of the holy and inſeparable Trinity is grounded on the Theological vertues of Faith, Hope, and Charitie) and whoſe foundation is happily eſtabliſhed vpon the moſt Chriſtian Kingdome of God, by pouring thy aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and moſt impious venime amongſt the impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall branches, and neareſt members of the ſame, (that the Pillars thereof beeing ſhaken, the whole building might fall to the ground) oftentimes haſt ſet vngodly diuiſion among the ſeauen Electors of the Empire, by whom (as by ſeuen Candleſtickes, ſhining in the vnitie of a ſeuen-fold Spirit) the holy Empire ſhould be illuminated.</p>
               <p>Therefore, by vertue of our office, which by the Imperiall Crowne we hold, to preuent the dangers of future diuiſions and diſſentions among the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, whereof (as being King of <hi>Bohemia</hi>) we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge our ſelfe to be one, by a double reaſon, as well of our Imperiall Commaund, as by our right of Election, which we execute, among other Lawes preſcribed for the nouriſhing and maintaining of
<pb facs="tcp:4347:3"/> correſpondencie among the Electors, and thereby to induce them vnto an vnitie of Election, and a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation of the afore-ſaid diuiſion, and to ſtop the paſſage vnto diuers perills thereby enſuing at an Imperiall aſſembly, holden in our Court at <hi>Norem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergh,</hi> in the preſence of all the Princes Electors, Spirituall and Temporall, and of a great number of other Princes, Earles, Barons, Knights, Gentlemen, and Burgeſſes of the Cities and Townes of our Empire, ſitting in our Throne, apparelled in our Imperiall Robes, and Crowne vpon our head, with mature deliberation, and by imperiall power, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine, declare, and eſtabliſh, &amp;c. In the yeare of our LORD GOD 1356. in the ninth <hi>Indiction,</hi> and the fourth <hi>Ides</hi> of <hi>Ianuary,</hi> and of our reigne the tenth of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and the firſt of our EMPIRE.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="proclamation">
               <head>In what manner the Electors are to be conducted to the Election, and by whom.</head>
               <p>VVE ordaine, and by this our preſent Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall Edict, perpetually to be obſerued, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund, of our meere motion and free Imperiall po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, that as often, and whenſoeuer, in time to come, vpon neceſſitie, or the cauſe of Election of the King of <hi>Romaines</hi> to be Emperour, it ſhall hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen and fall out, that the Princes Electors, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the auncient and laudable cuſtome for the ſaid Election, are to trauell, and ſet forward on their iourney, euery Prince Elector ſhall (vpon requeſt made by the ſaid Electors) be bound to conduct
<pb facs="tcp:4347:4"/> and accompany his co-Electors, when they are for that cauſe to trauell, through their territories, lands and iuriſdictions; and further alſo, as neceſſitie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth, and without refuſall, conuey them to the City or place where ſuch Election is to be made and celebrated, and alſo at their returne from thence, vpon paine of periurie, and loſſe (for that time onely) of his or their voyce, which he or they is, or are, to haue in the ſaid Election.</p>
               <p>Which ſaid penalties, to him or them, that ſhall ſhew themſelues rebellious, obſtinate, or negligent, in the ſaid conduction, we our ſelues will iudge and impoſe.</p>
               <p>Wee further ordaine and commaund all other Princes, Feodaries, and belonging to the Imperiall Iuriſdiction, by what name ſoeuer they are called, Dukes, Earles, Barons, Knights, and their Retai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, Gentlemen and others, Burgeſſes and Officers of Caſtles, Cities and places whatſoeuer of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Empire, that at ſuch time as the King of the <hi>Romains</hi> is to be elected Emperor, vpon requeſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them made by the Princes Electours, or any of them, for conduction, either of themſelues, or their Deputies, which they ſhall appoint, as aforeſaid, without any deniall, to conduct &amp; guide them tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row their territories, lands &amp; poſſeſſions, &amp; further, as need ſhall require. And that if they ſhall preſume or refuſe not to doe as wee herein ordaine and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point, they ſhall be liable to the paines and penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties heereafter following, <hi>viz.</hi> All Princes, Earles, Barons, Knights, Nobles and Gentlemen, doing the
<pb facs="tcp:4347:4"/> contrary, ſhall incurre the paine of guiltineſſe of periurie, and depriuation of all liberties and immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities whatſoeuer they hold and enioy by Imperiall right, or otherwiſe; as alſo of all other their offices and functions: And all Burgeſſes, and Commons of Cities and Townes, that preſume to doe the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, are likewiſe guiltie of periurie, and ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued of all the Rights, Liberties, Priuiledges, and Immunities, which by Imperiall libertie and graunt they hold and haue obtained; which together with their bodies and goods ſhall eſcheate and fall into the Emperours hands; and further, <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> be depriued of all Law and Right whatſoeuer; ſo that from thence-forth, it ſhall be lawfull for euery pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate man, of his owne authoritie, without lawfull proceedings, or aide of Magiſtrates, freely to aſſaile, and ſet vpon them, not once incurring any penalty, paine, or puniſhment whatſoeuer, by Imperiall au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, or otherwiſe, for the ſame, they being ſo conuinced for diſobedience againſt the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, and the ſacred ſtate and dignitie of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, as alſo againſt their owne honours and credits, and found to haue raſhly neglected their duties, and done as rebells, diſobedient ſubiects, and periured perſons againſt the Decree aforeſaide. Decreeing further, and commanding, That the Citizens and Inhabitants of all Towns and places where the ſayd Princes Electors, and either, or any of them, as alſo their Deputies, or their ſeruants ſhall lodge or reſt themſelues, in their iourney towards, or in the place of the Election aforeſaid, to ſell, and cauſe their
<pb facs="tcp:4347:5"/> victualls to be ſolde at the common rate and price accuſtomed, without inhauncing, or extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily raiſing the price of the ſame, vnto them and their retinue, for their neceſſary prouiſion; as alſo in their departure or returning home from thence againe. And whoſoeuer ſhall doe the contrary, we will that they ſhall incurre the ſame penalties that are formerly ſet downe againſt Citizens and others, for diſobedience in the caſes aforeſaid. Further, if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Princes, Earles, Barons, Knights, Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Burgeſſes, and Inhabitants of Townes and Cities whatſoeuer, ſhall offer to preſume malitiouſly to wrong or doe any iniury openly or priuily, by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny meanes whatſoeuer, vnto the Princes Electors in the way or otherwiſe, as they trauell to the place where the King of the <hi>Romains</hi> is to be elected, or in their returne from thence againe; or ſhall preſume to aſſaile or trouble them, or any of them, perſonal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or any of their Deputies aforeſayd, trauelling to and from the ſaid place, whether they ſhall demand conduction, or not, ſuch perſon or perſons, together with their adherents and complices, ſhall preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thereupon incurre the paines and puniſhments aforeſaid, euery man according to his ſtate, qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, and condition, as aforeſaid. And if any of the Princes Electors ſhall fall out or haue any particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar quarrell, contention, or controuerſie, one with or againſt the other, notwithſtanding the ſame, they ſhall be bound to conuey and conduct one the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or their Deputies by them appointed for the ſaid Election, to the place of Election, and backe
<pb facs="tcp:4347:5"/> againe as aforeſaid, vpon paine of incurring the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour of periurie, and the loſſe (for that time one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) of their voice in the Election, as aforeſaid. And if any other Princes, Earles, Barons, Knights, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, Citizens, or Commons of Townes what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, ſhall haue any particular quarrell with, or beare any euill will or enuy vnto, the Princes Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors in generall, or any of them in particular; or if that there ſhall ſodainely ariſe any quarrell, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, or warre betweene them; neuertheleſſe, all controuerſies and contentions ſet apart, they ſhall conduct the ſaid Prince, or Princes Electors, or his or their Deputies, appointed to goe to the ſaid Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, in their iourney both forward and backe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, as they will ſhunne and auoyde the paines and penalties aforeſaid, by vs ſet downe to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted vpon them that ſhall doe the contrarie, wherein we our ſelues will be Iudges, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>For the better and further eſtabliſhing and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming of all the premiſes, we will and command, That euery &amp; all the Princes Electors, and the reſt of the Earles, Barons, Knights, Gentlemen, Cities, Towns, &amp; Inhabitants thereof, ſhall, by their oaths, ſet downe in writing, vnder their hands, promiſe &amp; binde themſelues, to obſerue, fulfill, and keepe all the premiſes, in euery point faithfully and truely, according to the tenour thereof: And whoſoeuer ſhall deny or refuſe to doe the ſame, ſhall foorth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with incurre the paines and puniſhments, that are formerly inflicted vpon euery man, according to his or their eſtate and degree.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:4347:6"/>
               <p>If any Prince Elector, or any other Prince, of what eſtate or condition ſoeuer hee be, feodarie to the Empire, Earles, Barons or Knights, or any of their heires and ſucceſſors, ſhall not hold, performe, and obſerue our aforeſaid and enſuing conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and lawes, or preſume to contrarie the ſame, if the ſaid Prince Elector continue therein, then the reſt of the Electors ſhall from thence forward exclude him out of their company, and he ſhall be excluded from his voice of Election, and place of Elector among the reſt of the Electors; neither ſhall he enioy his feodarie preferments which he vſually had in the Empire: And all other Princes and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men aforeſaid, committing the like offence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our ſaid lawes, likewiſe, ſhall not enioy their feodary rights, by the Empire giuen and gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto them; and yet neuertheleſſe, they ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre the danger of all the paines and penalties a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, perſonally concerning them, according to their degrees and qualities, ordained and appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. And although all and euery one of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Earles, Barons, Knights, Gentlemen, Cities, Townes, and Burgeſſes of the ſame, are bound to conduct and accompany euery or any one of the ſaid Electors or their deputies as aforeſaid; neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe, we thinke it conuenient to ordaine and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point ſeuerall and fit conductors and conductions through the Countries, Townes, and Territories neere or neereſt adioyning vnto them, as hereafter more at large appeareth.</p>
               <p>Firſt, the King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> chiefe BVTLER, or
<pb facs="tcp:4347:6"/> Cup-bearer of the Empire, ſhall be conducted by the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Mentz,</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Bamburge,</hi> and <hi>Wirtzenburgh,</hi> the Burgeſſes of <hi>Wremburgh, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henloe, Werthen, Brunecke,</hi> and <hi>Hanow,</hi> the townes of <hi>Noremburgh, Rotenburgh,</hi> and <hi>Wyndeſhem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Collen,</hi> Chancelor for the Empire in <hi>Italie,</hi> ſhall be conducted by the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Mentz</hi> and <hi>Tride,</hi> the County <hi>Palatine</hi> of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> the Lantgraue of <hi>Heſſen,</hi> the Earles of <hi>Katſenellenboghen, Naſſaw, Dyetz, Iſenburgh, Weſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh, Runkell, Limburgh,</hi> and <hi>Valkenſtein,</hi> the cities of <hi>Wetflaria, Beylenhuyſen,</hi> and <hi>Fredebergh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Treuers,</hi> Chancelor for the Empire in <hi>France,</hi> and the Kingdome of <hi>Arles,</hi> ſhall be conducted by the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Mentz,</hi> the Earles Palatine of the <hi>Rhine, Spanheim</hi> and <hi>Veltentz,</hi> the Rhingraues of <hi>Wildegrauen, Naſſaw, Iſenburgh, Weſterburgh, Runkell, Limburgh, Dyetz, Katſenellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boghen, Eppenſtein,</hi> and <hi>Valkenſtein,</hi> and the Citie of <hi>Mentz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The county <hi>Palatine</hi> of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> chiefe SEVVER of the Empire, ſhall be conducted by the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Mentz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Duke of <hi>Saxon,</hi> Marſhall of the Empire, ſhall be conducted by the King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> the Arch-Biſhops of <hi>Mentz,</hi> and <hi>Madeburgh,</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Banburgh,</hi> and <hi>Wirtzenburgh,</hi> the Marques of <hi>Miſnia,</hi> the Lantgraue of <hi>Heſſen,</hi> the Abbots of <hi>Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> and <hi>Herffelden,</hi> the Burgraues of <hi>Noremburgh, Hohenloe, Wirthen, Brunecke, Hanow,</hi> and <hi>Valkenſtein,</hi> the Cities of <hi>Erford, Wulenhuyſen, Noremburgh,
<pb facs="tcp:4347:7"/> Rotenburgh,</hi> and <hi>Wyndelſthem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And all theſe laſt named ſhall conduct the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graue of <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> chiefe Chamberlaine of the Empire.</p>
               <p>Alſo wee will, and expreſly ordaine, that euery one of the Princes Electors that ſhall deſire any ſuch conduction, ſhall certifie thoſe that ſhall ſo by him be required, in ſuch conuenient time, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſignifie vnto them what way he intends to ride, that they that ſhall be thereunto required, may haue ſufficient time to prepare themſelues of all things neceſſary for the ſame.</p>
               <p>Theſe ordinances aforeſaid, concerning this conduction, our meaning is ſhall in ſuch ſort be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, that euery one aboue named, or others not named, that ſhall be required to conduct the ſaid Electors, ſhall be bound to prepare themſelues willingly and readily to doe it, not onely through their owne Lands and Territories, but further alſo, if neede require, vpon paine of the penalties afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid ſet downe.</p>
               <p>We further appoint and ordaine, that the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Mentz,</hi> that for the time ſhall be, ſhall by expreſſe meſſengers in writing ſignifie vnto euery one of the Princes his fellow Co-electors, both ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall and temporall, the ſaid Election, in which his Letters hee ſhall ſpecifie with as much ſpeede as thoſe Letters can conueniently come vnto their hands, the day on which within three moneths next after enſuing in the ſaid letters contained, al the ſaid Electors, are to be at <hi>Franckford</hi> vpon <hi>Maine,</hi> either
<pb facs="tcp:4347:7"/> in perſon or by his or their lawfull deputies there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto appointed, with full power and authority vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their hands and ſeales, to elect the King of the <hi>Romains</hi> to be Emperour. In what manner &amp; forme ſuch Letters ſhall be made, and perpetually penned, and in what manner and forme alſo the ſaid Princes Electors ſhall authorize their deputies in that caſe of Election by them ſo appointed to be done, at the end of this booke you ſhall finde it ſet downe, and more plainely expreſſed, which forme ſo ſet downe, by our imperiall power and authoritie wee doe commaund in that manner to be obſerued.</p>
               <p>And whenſoeuer it ſhall happen, that the death of the Emperour, or of the King of the <hi>Romaines,</hi> is knowne in the Dioceſſe of <hi>Mentz,</hi> then within a moneth from the day of the notice of the ſame, iuſtly accounted, our will and pleaſure is, that the ſaid Arch-Biſhop ſhall by his Letters ſignifie the ſame vnto euery one of the Princes Electors, in manner as aforeſaid; which if the ſaid Arch-Biſhop ſhall neglect or careleſly put off, then the ſaid Princes Electors ſhall of themſelues, without calling or warning (in performance of their oathes and alleagiance to the Empire) at the end of three mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths aforeſaid, as in the former inſtitution is decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, repaire to the ſaid towne of <hi>Franckford,</hi> there to proceede to the Election of the King of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains</hi> to be Emperour.</p>
               <p>And euery Prince Elector, or his deputie, ſhall enter into the ſaid towne of <hi>Franckford</hi> at the ſaid Election, with a trayne of, not aboue two hundred
<pb facs="tcp:4347:8"/> horſemen, and not more, whereof fiftie of them onely, and not aboue, ſhall be armed.</p>
               <p>And euery Prince Elector, that is called and ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned to the ſaid Election, not comming there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, nor yet ſending his lawfull deputie, with his Letters Patents vnder his hand and ſeale, with full power &amp; authority to elect the King of the <hi>Romains</hi> to be Emperour, or if after, the ſaid Prince, or the ſaid deputie, ſhall goe from the ſaid place of electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the King of the <hi>Romains</hi> not being elected to be Emperour, nor his ſaid deputie fully authorized, he ſhall loſe his voyce which he ought to haue in ſuch election.</p>
               <p>Wee alſo charge, commaund and enioyne the citizens of <hi>Franckford</hi> to defend and protect all the ſaid Princes Electors in generall, and euery one of them in particular, from all inuaſions or tumults that may happen among them, vpon any particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar diſlike, and alſo from all other men that may at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt any thing againſt them, and likewiſe their ſeruants and followers, which they or any of them ſhall bring, to the number of two hundred afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, into the ſaid Citie; and they ſhall take their corporall oathes vpon the holy Euangeliſts, for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance thereof, vpon paine of incurring the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of Periurie, together with the loſſe of all their Rights, Liberties, Priuiledges and Immunities, which by Emperiall authoritie they hold and enioy, and to fall into the danger of outlarie, both in bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and goods: and in that caſe it ſhall be lawfull for euery man, at his or their owne liberties, without
<pb facs="tcp:4347:8"/> orderly proceeding, to inuade and aſſault them and euery one of them, when they will, and at all times, (being thereby depriued of all Law, as traitors and Rebels to the Empire,) without any puniſhment to be inflicted on them for the ſame, neither within nor without the Empire. The ſaid citizens of <hi>Frankford</hi> alſo, during all the time of the ſaid Election, ſhall not ſuffer any man, of what eſtate or condition ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer he be, in any ſort to enter into the ſaid Towne, (the Princes Electors themſelues, and their depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties aforeſaid excepted) who are euery one of them to enter with two hundred horſe-men, as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid: And if after they are entred with their traines aforeſaid, or in their preſence, any man be found to be there, contrary to our decree; the ſaid Citizens preſently and with all ſpeede ſhall take order for his ſpeedy departure out of the Citie, without ſtay, vpon paine of incurring the penalties aforeſaid to be laid vpon them, or elſe of the breach of their oathes, which they are to take vpon the holy Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts for the performance of this our decree, as it is formerly expreſſed and declared.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="proclamation">
               <head>Touching the Election of the King of the <hi>Romaines.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AS ſoone as the ſaid Electors or their deputies are entred into the ſaid Citie of <hi>Franckford,</hi> the next day in the morning, in the Church of Saint <hi>Bartholomew,</hi> they ſhall cauſe the Maſſe of the holy Spirit to be ſung before them, to the end that the ſaid holy Spirit might open their hearts, and illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate
<pb facs="tcp:4347:9"/> their mindes, to chuſe and elect a good, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right and a fit perſon to be King of the <hi>Romaine,</hi> and Emperour, and for the aduancement of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian faith: And after the ſaid Maſſe, all the Electors, or their deputies, ſhall approach vnto the Alter on which the ſaid Maſſe was celebrated, where the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Princes Electors, ſtanding together with the temporall, the Goſpell of Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> (beginning, <hi>In principio erat verbum,</hi>) ſhall be laid open before them, the ſpirituall Princes reuerently laying their hands vpon their breſts, and the ſecular Princes lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their hands vpon the booke, in the preſence of all their company, who then are to be there ſhall take their oath, which oath the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Mentz</hi> ſhal giue vnto them, and ſhall openly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the ſame in this manner.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>J Arch-Biſhop of</hi> Mentz HIGH-CHANCELOR <hi>of the ſacred</hi> EMPIRE <hi>in</hi> Germany, <hi>and Prince Elector, ſweare to this holy Goſpell now laid before me, that vpon the alleagiance which I owe to God and to the Empire of</hi> Rome, <hi>I will with all my heart and beſt indeauour by Gods helpe, chuſe a temporall head for the people of Chriſtendome</hi> that is, <hi>a King of the Romains to be Emperour, ſuch an one as ſhall be fit and capable for the place, according to my alleagiance aforeſaid, and my voyce, and the voyces of the Electors, without any fraud, or other ſiniſter and particular dealing, by mee there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to be vſed, ſo helpe me God and all his holy Saints.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This oath in this manner being taken by the ſaid Electors, or their deputies, according to their ſaid oath, they ſhall proceed to the Election, and ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:4347:9"/> not in any manner depart out of the ſaid Citie of <hi>Franckford,</hi> before that the greater ſort of them ſhall haue choſen a temporall head or gouernour of the world, or of Chriſtendome, a King of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains,</hi> to be Emperour; which if they ſhall prolong or deferre the ſpace of thirty dayes from the day of taking their oathes, then the ſaid thirty dayes being expired, they ſhall eate nothing but bread and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, nor by any meanes goe away from the ſaid Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, vntill or before they or the greater number of them ſhall haue choſen the ruler or temporall head of Chriſtendome, as aforeſaid. And after that in the ſame place, they or the greater part of them ſhall haue made their Election, the ſame ſhall be as lawfull and good, as if it had beene made by the voice and conſent of them altogether, without gayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaying, and ſo ſhall be celebrated. And if it ſhall hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen that any of the Electors, or their deputies afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, ſhall ſtay longer from comming to <hi>Franckford</hi> to the Election, then the time appointed; yet if hee or they ſhall come thither before the ſaid Election i<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> made, wee ordaine and decree that he or they ſhall neuertheleſſe be admitted to the ſaid Election, as well as if they had come thither at the firſt day and time aforeſaid, which in the ſame manner wee will and commaund to be continually and perpetually obſerued. Wee alſo ordaine, and by our imperiall power and authority commaund, that hee, who in manner aforeſaid ſhall be choſen to be King of <hi>Romains,</hi> the Election being made, before hee ſhall doe any thing, or proceed to the ordering of any
<pb facs="tcp:4347:10"/> affaires whatſoeuer, touching the Empire, by vertue of his place and dignitie of King of <hi>Romains,</hi> he ſhall by his Letters Patents confirme all the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledges, rights, liberties, graunts, auncient cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes, and dignities vnto the Princes Electors both Spirituall and Temporall, which are knowne and reputed to be the principalleſt members of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, and whatſoeuer elſe they ſhall haue obtained and enioyed in the Empire vntill the day of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection; and when hee ſhall be crowned Emperour, he ſhall ratefie and confirme the ſame vnto all the Electors in generall, &amp; euery one of them in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, without any denyall or contradiction whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer. And in caſe wheras three Princes Electors, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, or their deputies in their abſence, ſhall together chuſe one of the Princes Electors, either preſent or abſent, to be King of <hi>Romains;</hi> the voyce of him that is Elected, (if he be preſent, or his deputie in his abſence,) ſhall be of ſufficient power and means to encreaſe the greater number of the Election, and to make the ſame as effectuall, and of as good force, as if it had beene made by all the Electors together.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="proclamation">
               <head>The manner how the Spirituall Princes Electors ſhall ſit by the Emper<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur, when he is ſet in his Imperiall Throne.</head>
               <head type="sub">In the name of the holy and inſeparable Trinitie. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>CHarles</hi> the fourth, by the diuine grace of God, Emperour of <hi>Rome, Semper Auguſtus,</hi> and King
<pb facs="tcp:4347:10"/> of <hi>Bohemia;</hi> in perpetuall memorie, and for the glory and grace of the holy Empire, the honour of the Emperour, and for an order hereafter to be preſcribed to the common-wealth, to the end that the moſt reuerent and illuſtrious Princes Electors, may be maintained in peace and vnity of minde, who as principall pillers, circumſpectly, prudent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, wiſely, and holily, ſuſtaine, ſupport and vphold the ſacred edifice of the Empire, and whoſe aſſiſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and aydes ſtrengthen and corroborate the right hand of the imperiall power; and how much the more by mutuall fauour and ample dignitie they are vnited together, ſo much the more peace and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility and commodity the people of Chriſtendome thereby obtaine and enioy: therefore that among the venerable Arch-Biſhops and Prelates of <hi>Mentz, Collen,</hi> and <hi>Tryer,</hi> Princes Electors of the ſacred Empire, all diſſention, ſuſpition, and contention touching Superiority, or ſitting in counſell, in the imperiall Courts, and reſorts, that may ariſe or grow hereafter, may be cut off and ceaſed, and that they being peaceable and quiet in minde may the better and freelyer conſider of the important af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of the Empire, and with one will, and conſent, and vnity, meditate thereon, for the conſolation and comfort of the chriſtian people: By the counſell and deliberation of all the Princes Electors, both ſpirituall and temporall, wee Decree, and by our imperiall power and authoritie ordaine, this Order and Law, perpetually to be obſerued, that the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid reuerent Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Tryer,</hi> ſhall ſit oppoſite
<pb facs="tcp:4347:11"/> right before the Emperors face. The Arch-biſhop of <hi>Mentz,</hi> in his owne Dioceſſe and Prouinces, and alſo out of his Prouinces in al his Chancelours regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment throughout <hi>Germany,</hi> the Prouince of <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len</hi> onely excepted: And the Archbiſhop of <hi>Collen</hi> in his Dioceſſe and Prouinces, and out of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces throughout all <hi>Italie,</hi> may, ſhall, and ought to ſit on the right hand of the Emperour of <hi>Rome,</hi> in all publique actes, Imperial Iudgements, Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, Feodarie Courts, Feaſts, Counſels, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther actions, which may happen and fall out for the ſeruice and honour of the Empire: which mutuall order aforeſaid, of ſitting, ſo appoynted for them, wee ordaine and command to be obſerued and kept among the ſaid Arch-biſhops of <hi>Collen, Tryer,</hi> and <hi>Mentz,</hi> and their Succeſſors for euer, that hereafter no contention or diſtaſte may, for the ſame, grow and breed among them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="proclamation">
               <head>Touching all the Electors ſitting in the Emperours preſence.</head>
               <p>VVEe further ordaine, That whenſoeuer the Emperour ſhall holde his Imperiall Court of Parliament, in euery Seſſion, as well in Counſell, as in Parliament, and at meate, or any other place whatſoeuer, where the Emperour and the King of <hi>Romaines</hi> ſhall happen to ſit with the Princes E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectors, next after the Arch-biſhops of <hi>Mentz,</hi> or <hi>Collen,</hi> which of them, at that time, in regard of the qualitie of their places, or varietie of Prouinces,
<pb facs="tcp:4347:11"/> and his other Priuiledges, ſhall be ſet downe on the right hand of the Emperour, the King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> being an annoynted and a crowned Prince, ſhall ſit next vnto him; the Earle <hi>Palatine</hi> of the <hi>Rheine,</hi> ſhal haue the next place on the left ſide of the Emperor, after, one of the Arch-biſhops aforeſaid, whoſe chance it ſhall be then to ſit on the left ſide of the Emperour. Then the Duke of <hi>Saxon;</hi> and after him the Margraue of <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> ſhall ſit downe: But, when, and as often as the Emperours ſhall be dead, then the Arch-biſhop of <hi>Mentz</hi> ſhall haue power, as it is formerly ſet downe, by Letters, to ſummon all the Princes aforeſaid, to come together for the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection; who being all, or as many of them as can or will come, within the time of election, aſſembled, the ſaid Arch-biſhop of <hi>Mentz,</hi> and none other, ſhal aske euery one of his fellow Electors, their voice in the election, as followeth: Firſt, the Arch-biſhop of <hi>Tryer,</hi> whom we ordaine to ſpeake firſt, &amp; to whom we find that it hath ſtill belonged: Then the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Collen,</hi> to whom it belongeth to crowne the King of <hi>Romaines:</hi> The third, the King of <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia,</hi> who amongſt the Temporall Electors, in regard of his Royall dignity, is the chiefe of them: The fourth, the Earle <hi>Palatine</hi> of the <hi>Rheine:</hi> The fift, the Duke of <hi>Saxon:</hi> and the ſixt, the Margraue of <hi>Brandenburgh:</hi> who ſitting orderly, the Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Mentz,</hi> ſhall aske euery one of them, whom they will chooſe, or giue their conſent vnto.</p>
               <p>Further, in the celebration of the Imperiall Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the Margraue of <hi>Brandenburgh</hi> ſhall holde the
<pb facs="tcp:4347:12"/> Baſon, whileſt the Emperour or King of <hi>Romains</hi> waſh his or their hands: Next, the King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> ſhall beare the Kings cup to drinke, which, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his regall Crowne, and according to the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledge of his kingdome, vnleſſe he will voluntari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doe it, he is not bound to doe: The Earle <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latine</hi> of the <hi>Rheine,</hi> ſhall ſerue in the firſt diſh; and the Duke of <hi>Saxon,</hi> ſhall exerciſe the place of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall, as he hath anciently vſed to doe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="proclamation">
               <head>The Priuiledges of the Earle <hi>PALATINE</hi> of the <hi>Rheine,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Saxon.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AS often as the Empire ſhall happen to be void, the illuſtrious Earle <hi>Palatine</hi> of the <hi>Rheine,</hi> chiefe Sewer of the Empire, in place of the future King of <hi>Romains,</hi> by right and priuiledge of his Earledome, ought to bee Oner-ſeer in the territories of the <hi>Rheine, Sweuia,</hi> and <hi>Franconia,</hi> for the Emperor; with power of exerciſing Iuſtice, preſentation of Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall Benefices, receiuing Rents and Reuenews, and in the name of the Empire, to take the oaths of fidelitie and feoffments; which neuertheleſſe, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the King of <hi>Romaines</hi> is elected, ſhall all bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iterated, and they ſhall againe renew their oathes vnto him, the oathes of the Princes, and of thoſe that are called <hi>Vanlehen</hi> excepted, which we ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally reſerue for the Emperour himſelfe, or the King of <hi>Romains:</hi> but all kindes of Alienations, or Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations of Imperial things, are excluded out of his power. The like power of Ouer-ſeer, we giue and
<pb facs="tcp:4347:12"/> appoynt vnto the illuſtrious Prince the Duke of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xon,</hi> as Marſhal of the Empire, in thoſe places where the Iuriſdiction of <hi>Saxon</hi> extend, in like manner and forme as aforeſaide: and although in the interim that the Emperour or King of <hi>Romaines</hi> are to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, Iuſtice ſhall be done by the Earle <hi>Palatine,</hi> as chiefe Sewer, and Prince Elector; yet the County <hi>Palatine</hi> ſhall not execute the ſaide Iudgement in any other place, then openly in the Emperours Court, where the Emperour himſelfe, or the King of <hi>Romains,</hi> if they were preſent, ſhould doe it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="proclamation">
               <head>How the Princes Electors ſhall take place before other Princes and Noble men of the Empire.</head>
               <p>VVEe further ordaine, That whenſoeuer, and as often as the Emperour ſhall ſummon a Court of Parliament; the Princes Electors afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd, both Spirituall and Temporall, according to the order preſcribed, ſhall ſit on the right and left hands of the Emperour, and ſo holde their places, and no other Prince, of what degree, ſtate, or condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſoeuer he be, in any place within the ſaid Court, in going, ſitting, or ſtanding, ſhall be preferred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them. And this is ſpecially to be obſerued, and noted, that the King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> at the celebration of the ſaid Court of Parliament, in all and euery the actions aforeſaid, (what other King, Prince, or Princes, of what eſtate ſoeuer he or they be, that may vpon any occaſion be preſent therein,) ſhall haue the preheminence and preferment of ſitting before him or them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="proclamation">
               <pb facs="tcp:4347:13"/>
               <head>Touching the Succeſsion of the Temporall Princes, Electors.</head>
               <p>AMong the innumerable cares wherewith wee are buſied for the maintenance of the happy ſtate of the Empire, by the ayde and helpe of God, our heart and minde daily laboureth to this end, that a deſired and wholeſome vnion may alwayes be had and maintained, with ſinceritie of heart, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Princes Electors of the Empire, whoſe prouidence, in time, will ſo much the ſooner and eaſelier appeare, and take effect, when no errour ſhall ariſe among them, and thereby Charity better obſerued, difficulty preuented, and right and equitie giuen to euery man. It is generally, manifeſtly, and publiquely knowne to all men, farre and neare, that the illuſtrious Princes, the King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> the County <hi>Palatine</hi> of the <hi>Rheine,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Saxon,</hi> and the Margraue of <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> by vertue of his Kingdome, and their Principalities, in the election of the King of <hi>Romains</hi> to be Emperour, with the reſt of the Spirituall Princes their Co-electors, by right haue their Places and Voices, and together with them, to chooſe them, as true and lawfull E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectors of the Empire: leſt that among the ſayde Temporall Princes ſonnes, in time to come, there may grow or ariſe any trouble, diſſention or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, touching the right, voyce and power of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection aforeſayd, and thereby to preuent all future impediments, lets, and hinderances therein, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring
<pb facs="tcp:4347:13"/> (by Gods help) carefully and wiſely to ſtay and ſtop all dangers, We ordaine, and by our Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall authority commaund, this preſent Law per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually to be obſerued and kept; That whenſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the ſayd temporall Princes, Electors, or any of them ſhall leaue their right, voyce, and power of election aforeſayd, the ſame ſhall iuſtly, lawfully and freely eſcheat and fall to the eldeſt ſonne and heire of him or them, being a Temporall perſon, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any contradiction whatſoeuer: And if the ſaid eldeſt ſonne, ſhall die without lawfull temporall heires male, by vertue of this our Imperiall Edict, the right, voyce, and power aforeſaid, ſhall fall to the next brother, being a Temporall perſon, right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſcending from his father; and after him, to his eldeſt ſonne, being a Temporall Prince: And ſuch ſucceſſion from the eldeſt ſonnes and heires of the ſaid Princes, in the right, voyce, and power afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid of election, ſhall from time to time perpetually be obſerued; with this condition and clauſe neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe, That if the ſaid Prince Elector, or his eldeſt ſonne, beeing a Temporall perſon, ſhall die, and leaue his heires male, being Temporall perſons, at the time of his deceaſe, vnder age, then the next bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the ſaid eldeſt ſonne, ſhall be tutor, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrator of the ſaid children, vntill the eldeſt of them ſhall attaine to lawfull yeares: whom we doe ordaine and appoint to be Elector, at the age of eighteene yeares, and at that time, the ſaid right, power, and voyce, and other appendances thereof, ſhall eſcheate vnto him: and then the ſaid admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrator
<pb facs="tcp:4347:14"/> ſhall reſigne the ſaid office and rights afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid wholly vnto him. And if any of the ſaid Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces houſes ſhall happen to faile, and be extingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, for want of heires male; then the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour or King of <hi>Romaines,</hi> for the time being, ſhall and may take order therein, and prouide an other Elector, as an eſcheate lawfully fallen to him and the Emperour, alwayes excepting the priuiledges, rights, and cuſtomes of our Kingdome of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> touching the election of their King, in caſe of vaca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by the Subiects thereof, that haue right and authoritie to elect their King: Obſeruing their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uileges, and ancient cuſtomes continually vſed, and by diuers Emperours of <hi>Rome,</hi> or Kings, graunted vnto them, which by this our Decree wee will by no meanes breake nor infringe, but rather confirme the ſame, from hence forward, to be and remayne in as full power and effect as heeretofore they haue beene, and ſo for euer to continue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="proclamation">
               <head>Of the immunities and priuiledges of the Kings of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects thereof.</head>
               <p>WHereas by two illuſtrious Emperours of <hi>Rome,</hi> and Kings of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> our Progenitors and Predeceſſors, it was giuen and graunted vnto the ſayd Kingdome and Crowne, and at this preſent, in the ſaid Kingdome, from time out of minde, is and hath beene a laudable cuſtome and law with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any contradiction, and miſ-conſtruction, vſed
<pb facs="tcp:4347:14"/> among them, that no Prince, Baron, Knight, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, retainers to Nobles, Burgeſſes, Citizens, nor any other perſon or perſons of the ſaid King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, or their adherents, of what eſtate, dignitie, preheminence, or condition ſoeuer they be, at any mans ſuite or ſummons whatſoeuer, ſhall be called, cited, warned, or ſummoned to appeare before any Iudge, or Iudgement Seate, Court of Law or Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice whatſoeuer, out of the Realme of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and the Courts of law and equity therein holden, which time out of minde, hath ſo beene holden and vſed among them: Wee therefore, to renew and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme the ſame Priuiledge, cuſtome and indulgence, graunted them by Imperiall authoritie aforeſayd, of our ſpeciall grace, and by our Imperiall authoritie, doe ordaine, That if any Prince, Baron, Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, Knight, Gentleman, retainers to Nobles, Burgeſſes, Citizens, Peaſants, or any other perſon or perſons of the ſaide Realme and Kingdome, ſhall be ſummoned, warned, or adioyned to appeare or anſwere to and before any Iudge, Iudgement Seate, Court of Lawe, or Iuſtice, out of the Realme and Kingdome of <hi>Bohemia</hi> aforeſaid, either for any cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minall, ciuill, or any other cauſe or action whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, and at any time or times what or whereſoeuer, they are not in any manner or ſort bound to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare or anſwere to the ſame; and if that, for not appearing or anſwering, at, or before any ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>competent Iudge or Iudgement Seate, or whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer authorities out of the Realme of <hi>Bohemia</hi> afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, their aduerſe parties ſhall in ſuch manner pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed
<pb facs="tcp:4347:15"/> againſt them, and that Sentence definitiue, or execution thereupon, ſhalbe giuen and pronounced in any cauſe whatſoeuer in thoſe Courts againſt them, by forraine authoritie as aforeſaid: We or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine, appoynt, and iudge the ſaid Citations, ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, precepts, proceſſes, ſentences and executions thereupon enſewing, and all things, which by the ſame, or any of thoſe meanes, ſhall, or may follow, be done, &amp; attempted, in that manner againſt them, to be vtterly void, diſannulled, and of no force nor effect. Further adding, and expreſly ordering, by our ſaide Imperiall authoritie, for euer to bee held, That although in the ſaid Realme of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> (time out of mind) the ſame hath alwaies beene obſerued, if from hence forth any Prince, Baron, Nobleman, Knight, or retainer to Nobles, Citizens, Burgeſſes, Peaſants, or any Subiects of the Realme of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> of what eſtate, preheminence, dignitie, or conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſoeuer he be, in any proceſſe, ſentence defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, precepts of the King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> or any of their Iudgements and executions thereof, made, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced and executed againſt them in Iudgement, eyther before the King, or the tribunall Seates of iudgement in the ſaid realme, thereunto commonly appoynted, ſhall appeale to any other Iudge or Iudgement ſeate out of the realme of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer he be that ſhall doe ſo, and if the partie De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant doth not reſiſt nor gaine-ſay the Plaintife, both the Defendant and Plaintife, in that caſe, ſhall incurre the danger of looſing their ſuite.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="proclamation">
               <pb facs="tcp:4347:15"/>
               <head>Of Gold, Siluer, and other kindes of Mettals.</head>
               <p>THis preſent ſtatute we ordaine for euer to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, and thereby declare that our ſucceſſors, Kings of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> as alſo all and euery one of the Princes Electors, both ſpirituall and temporall, which for the time perpetually ſhall be, ſhall law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully haue, hold, enioy, and poſſeſſe all Mines of ſuch Gold, Siluer, Tinne, Copper, Iron, Leade, and other kindes of Mettals, and alſo of Salt already found, or hereafter to be found, as at any time here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore were within the ſaid Realme of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> or the territories thereof: And likewiſe, that the ſaid Princes Electors, in the prouinces, parts, lands, in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular dominions, and territories to them or any of them appertaining, ſhal lawfully poſſeſſe &amp; hold and enioy the ſame, together with all rights whatſoeuer, (none excepted) whereby they might, may, and were wont to holde and poſſeſſe the ſame, as alſo to take lawfull towles and cuſtomes, heretofore giuen and graunted vnto them for the ſame, &amp; which our Progenitors, Kings of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and the ſaid Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces Electors, and their Predeceſſors and Progenitors lawfully might claime, vntill this time, according to the auncient, laudable, and approued cuſtome at this day, and long time before, vſed and obſerued.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="proclamation">
               <head>Touching Money.</head>
               <p>VVE alſo ordaine, that the King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> our ſucceſſour, that for the time ſhall be, as it appeareth, that the illuſtrious Kings of <hi>Bohemia</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4347:16"/> our predeceſſors, were wont to haue and peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly vſed in former times, ſhall haue the vſe, libertie, and cuſtome of Coyning, Making, and vttering of Money ſtamped, in Gold and Siluer, in all places and parts of the ſaid Realme, or territories there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, where the ſaid King ſhall be pleaſed to Coyne, and make the ſame, in what ſort, faſhion, &amp; ſtampe ſoeuer they will, as vntill this time, it hath been, and ſhall perpetually be vſed. And further, wee giue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Kings of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> by this our imperial Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, libertie to authorize the Princes, Nobles, Earles and other perſons of the ſaid Realme, to buy Lands, Caſtles, Poſſeſſions, goods and Morgages, whatſoeuer or whereſoeuer in the Empire, or to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue and take them of guift by any manner or meanes whatſoeuer, according to the tenour of the ſaid Lands, Caſtles, Poſſeſſions, Morgages, or goods accuſtomed; ſo that Free-hold, may be bought for Free-hold, Coppy-hold as coppy-hold, Feodarie as Feodarie, and ſhall in ſuch ſort be hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, that whatſoeuer the Kings of <hi>Bohemia</hi> ſhall buy or receiue, and ſhall be applied to the vſe and benefit of the ſaid Realme, ſhall continue to yeeld and pay the accuſtomed and ordained quit-rents and tallages due from them vnto the Empire. This preſent conſtitution, grace and fauour of our Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall Maieſtie, ſo graunted to the Realme of <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia,</hi> wee alſo giue and graunt vnto all the Princes Electors, as well ſpirituall and temporall, as alſo to their lawfull heires and ſucceſſours, in all points as it is formerly declared.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="proclamation">
               <pb facs="tcp:4347:16"/>
               <head>The Immunities and priuiledges, of the Princes Electors.</head>
               <p>VVEe ordaine and decree alſo, that no Earles, Barons, Nobles, feodarie Vaſſailes, Knights, Citizens, Burgeſſes, nor any other perſon ſubiect to the Eccleſiaſticall Iuriſdictions of <hi>Mentz, Tryer</hi> and <hi>Collen,</hi> of what ſtate, condition, or digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſoeuer they be, ſhall not vpon occaſion, or by any procurement whatſoeuer, be cited or ſummo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to appeare, without the Territories, Bounds and Limits of the ſaid Churches, and the appur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenances thereof, before any other Tribunall ſeate or place of Iuſtice or Iudgement, then onely in the liberties and iuriſdiction of <hi>Mentz, Tryer</hi> and <hi>Collen,</hi> and before the Iudges thereof, in time to come, nor hereafter, according to the cuſtome of the ſaid churches in times paſt obſerued. And that if contrary to this our preſent Edict, the ſubiects of the Churches of <hi>Mentz, Tryer,</hi> and <hi>Collen,</hi> or any of them, vpon any occaſion whatſoeuer, ſhal chance to be cited or ſummoned to appeare before any tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunall ſeate, for any criminall, ciuill, or other cauſe or buſineſſe out of the limits and territories of the ſaid Churches, or any of them, they ſhall not be bound to appeare, nor in any ſort to anſwere there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, as alſo that the Citations, Proceſſes, and Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, diffinitiues, or otherwiſe, againſt them begun, for not appearing before ſuch forraine Iudges, or hereafter to be made and pronounced, as alſo the
<pb facs="tcp:4347:17"/> precepts and executions of the ſame, and all things which from them, or any of them, or by that means ſhall or may be done and attempted, are and ſhall be voide and of none effect; expreſly commaunding, that no Earle, Baron, feodarie Vaſſall, Knights, Citizens, Burgeſſes, Peaſants, nor any other perſon, ſubiects to the ſaid Churches, or their inhabitants, of what eſtate, condition, or dignitie ſoeuer they be, ſhall appeale from the proceſſes, ſentences defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue or other, &amp; precepts of the ſaid Arch-Biſhops, and their Churches, or the executions therof made &amp; pronounced, or to be made and pronounced againſt them, in the Arch-Biſhopricke or their Conſiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries &amp; tribunall ſeates, as long as they are not deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Law and Iuſtice in the Arch-Biſhoprickes, nor their Conſiſtories aforeſaid; and that ſuch appeales in that ſort made, ſhall not be receiued, accepted, nor allowed, but to the contrary, ſhall be voide, and of none effect. But for want of Iuſtice, they and euery one of them may immediately appeale from them to the imperiall Court and tribunal ſeate of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror, &amp; not to any other Court whatſoeuer, either ordinarie or extraordinary; &amp; that whatſoeuer, ſhall be done, contrarie to the premiſſes, wee pronounce it to be voyde and of none effect. The ſame Law, Order, and Statute by vertue of this our Imperiall Decree, the illuſtrious Duke of <hi>Palatine</hi> of the <hi>Rheine,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Saxon,</hi> and the Marques of <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> temporall Princes Electors, and their heires, ſucceſſors, and ſubiects, ſhall alſo hold and enioy, in manner and forme as aforeſaid.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="proclamation">
               <pb facs="tcp:4347:17"/>
               <head>Touching the aſſembling or meeting of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces Electors.</head>
               <p>AMong many other cares, wherewith wee are daily buſied, it ſeemeth much to import our greatneſſe and ſublimitie, that the Princes Electors of the ſacred Empire, ſhould often meete and aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble together, to ſit about and conſult vpon the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of the Empire, and the good of Chriſtendome in generall: Which ſound pillers and ſtedfaſt and immoueable ſupporters of the Empire, as they are a great way diſtant one from another, on the other ſide, meeting in counſell, they may conſult vpon the defects of the Countries and Territories about them, by comming and conferring together, and by their wholeſome and ſound counſels apply good remedies thereunto: And to that end, we haue or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained our generall meeting in <hi>Noremburgh,</hi> with the Venerable, Eccleſiaſticall, and Illuſtrious tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall Princes Electors, and many other Princes and Nobles of the Empire, there, with good delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and their counſell and aduiſe, for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good of the Empire, to conſult with the ſaid Princes Electors, eccleſiaſticall and temporall. It is further by vs thought good, that the ſaid Princes Electors, from henceforth, euery yeare once after the feaſt of the Reſurrection of our Sauiour <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> commonly called <hi>Eaſter,</hi> for the ſpace of foure weeks together, ſhall meet &amp; aſſemble in ſome one of our imperiall Cities, and at the ſame time to
<pb facs="tcp:4347:18"/> come or enſew in the next yeare, the ſame meeting or counſell to be holden by vs and the ſaid Princes in our imperiall Citie of <hi>Vianna</hi> in <hi>Auſtria;</hi> and then at that place by our ſaid Counſell, it ſhall be deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined vpon the place where wee ſhall meete againe the next yeare, for the ſame purpoſe; this our order to hold no longer then we and our Counſell ſhal be pleaſed to continue it: &amp; during the aſſemblies afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, wee will defend and protect them by our im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall conduction, both comming to, ſtaying, and departing from thence. Further, leſt the furtherance of the common good and peace of the Empire, might by too much ſolacing, or exceſſiue frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of banquets be delayed, and put off, as many times it falleth out, and happeneth to be ſo; wee haue agreed, that from henceforth, while this mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting aforeſaid ſhall hold, it ſhall not be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to call and aſſemble any generall Court of all the Princes of the Empire together, in any other place; particular aſſemblies and expeditions mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately aſſembled, onely excepted.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="proclamation">
               <head>Priuiledges.</head>
               <p>VVEe further ordaine, and ſet downe for a perpetuall imperiall Law, that all Priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, and letters pattents of any perſon or perſons, of what eſtate, preheminence or dignitie ſoeuer hee or they be, or of any Cities. Townes or Vniuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, &amp;c. whereby any rights, graces, immunities, cuſtomes, or any other things, either by vs or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb facs="tcp:4347:18"/> by the Emperours and Kings our predeceſſors, in any manner or forme of words hath vnto them beene graunted, or that are to be graunted, by vs or our ſucceſſors, Emperours &amp; kings, in time to come, neither ſhall, may, nor ought at all to derogate and contrarie the liberties, iuriſdictions, rights, honours, and dominions of the Princes Electors, temporall, eccleſiaſticall, or of any of them in particular, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, that in ſuch priuiledges, and Letters pattents, made to any perſon of what eſtate, digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, or quallitie ſoeuer they be, as aforeſaid, or to any Vniuerſity, it be or ſhall be expreſly ſet downe ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, that they ſhall be irreuocable. If the ſaid pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledges and immunities be not found any wayes to derogate or contrary the priuiledges, liberties, iuriſdictions, rights, honours and dominions, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, of the ſaid Princes Electors or any of them; if otherwiſe wee cenſure them to be reuocable, and to be diſanulled; and by theſe preſents, vnderſtand, repute, and hold them to be reuoked.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="proclamation">
               <head>Of thoſe to whom as vnworthy thereof, Feoffments are made.</head>
               <p>IN diuers parts and places, the feodaries, vaſſails of lands &amp; benefices, which they haue peaceably ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained from their Lords often times by word of mouth, and fraudulently paſſe them ouer againe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their ſaid Lords; which hauing done, they defie and malitiouſly fall out with their ſaid Lords, and thereby wrong them, and vnder pretence of warre,
<pb facs="tcp:4347:19"/> or enmitie, re-enter vpon the ſame, and forcibly hold and poſſeſſe them: Therefore, this preſent law ſhall for euer be obſerued, that ſuch reſignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or ſurrenders ſhall be held and eſteemed to be voide and of no value, vnleſſe they be freely, order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and lawfully paſt ouer, in ſuch manner, that the ſaid benefices, &amp; feoffments may be really &amp; effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally aſſigned into the Lords hands againe, that ſo in time to come, there may no quarrell nor claime be made for them with the Lords, either by themſelues or any other in their names, or by the counſel, aide or procurement of them, or of any man whatſoeuer; And doing to the contrarie, or troubling and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſting the Lords for the ſaid benefices and feoff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, reſigned or not reſigned, or doing them any wrong, or counſelling, aiding, or abetting others againſt them, in that caſe they ſhall loſe their ſaid benefices and feoffments, and be accounted, hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den and eſteemed to be infamous perſons, and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawes, and not worthy to enioy or repoſſeſſe the ſame, by any meanes: and if by any new contract, or bargaine by them made with their ſaid Lords, they ſhall at any time be remitted into the ſame, by all manner of conſtruction, the ſaid feoffment ſhall be voyde and of no effect. Laſtly, wee will and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine that they or any of them that ſhall not frau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulently make ſuch reſignations vnto their Lords, and yet afterward trouble them for the ſame, or fraudulently making them, wilfully moleſt, inuade, and aſſaile them by force of this our-imperiall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, ſhall incurre all the penalties aforeſaid.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="proclamation">
               <pb facs="tcp:4347:19"/>
               <head>Of Conſpiracies.</head>
               <p>FVrther, deteſting (as our Lawes import) all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies, aſſemblies, or vnlawfull confederati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, made, either in, or out of Cities, or betweene Cities and Cities, perſons and perſons, or perſons priuate and Cities, (vnder pretence of banquets, or meetings of friends and Citizens at funerall feaſts, &amp;c.) thoſe kinde of aſſemblies, confederations, or compacts, as alſo the cuſtomes of the ſame, we cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to be corrupt, and doe reprooue, condemne, and vpon good aduice diſallow and diſanull them) of what eſtate, dignitie, or degree ſoeuer they be, either among themſelues, or without the authoritie of the Lords, whoſe ſubiects or miniſters, or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whoſe Iuriſdictions they are, (their ſaid Lords not excepted) or ſhall from henceforth doe, or in time to come preſume to doe, as by the ſacred Lawes of our excellent, imperiall predeceſſors, they are without doubt prohibited, and diſanulled: thoſe confederacies and Lawes excepted, which Princes, Cities, and others, for the generall peace of their Prouinces and Countries ſhall make, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude and agree vpon among themſelues: which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in our Decree ſpecially reſerued, we iudge to be and remaine in force and vigour; vntil by vs other order ſhall be taken for the ſame;) And conclude, that if any particular perſon, contrary to the tenor of this our Decree, and the ancient Lawes made concerning the ſame, ſhall hereafter enter into any
<pb facs="tcp:4347:20"/> other confederacies, meetings, conſpiracies, and compacts: beſides the penalties for the ſame ſet downe in the Lawes, they ſhall incurre the danger of infamie, and the forfeiture of ten pounds; and thoſe Cities or Vniuerſities, that ſhall (in that caſe) doe contrary to our ſaid Lawes, the forfeiture of an hundred pounds, together with the loſſe and depriuation of their Imperiall liberties and priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges; the one halfe of their ſaid forfeitures, to be payd into the Emperours Exchequer, and the other halfe to the Lord of the place, in whoſe Iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction the ſame was committed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="proclamation">
               <head>Of Pſalburgerie.</head>
               <p>BEcauſe no Citizens and Subiects to Princes, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons, or ſuch like perſons, ſhall ſeeke to caſt off the originall yoke of ſubiection (as they oftentimes doe complaine thereof vnto vs) and to that end boldely procure their admiſſion to dwell and inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite in other Cities, and often in times paſt practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the ſame, and neuertheleſſe ſtill hold their Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledges in thoſe Cities, Lands, Townes and Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, wherein they formerly reſided, and yet ſeeke to enioy the Liberties and Freedomes of thoſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces whereunto they ſo remoue, and claime protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſame, which in <hi>Germany</hi> was wont com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly to be called <hi>Pſalburgerie;</hi> To the end that no deceit nor guile ſhould in ſuch caſes be fauoured or vpholden, by our Imperiall power, together with the counſell and aduice of all the Princes Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors,
<pb facs="tcp:4347:20"/> both Spirituall and Temporall, we will and ordaine this Law, perpetually to be holden, That ſuch Citizens and their Subiects, ſo deluding or fraudulently dealing, in all the territories, places, and prouinces of the Empire, from this day for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, as ſo fraudulently procure, and hereafter ſhall procure themſelues to be entertained, and to dwell in other cities, ſhall not in the ſame Cities enioy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny rights or liberties whatſoeuer; vnleſſe they dwell corporally in the ſaid Citie, and therein continually keep houſe, and truly, and not fainedly, reſide in the ſame, paying Lot and Scot due and payable there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. And if any, contrary to the tenour of this our Decree, are or ſhall be ſo receiued, from hence-forth ſuch their acceptance or receiuing ſhall be voyde, and of no force, and ſuch as are ſo receiued, of what dignitie, condition or ſtate ſoeuer they be, from hence-forth in no manner ſhall enioy any rights or liberties within the ſaide Cities whatſoeuer, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding any rights, priuiledges or cuſtomes by them obtained, vſed, or obſerued in former times: Which, in as much, or ſo farre, as they are contrary to this our Decree, we doe hereby reuoke, and by our Imperiall power and authoritie, pronounce them to be voyde of all vigor and force. Touching the premiſes, concerning the Princes, Lords, and others, which ſhall happen ſo, or hereafter, to be forſaken by their Subiects, their rights in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and goods of their Subiects that ſo ſhall leaue them, alwayes excepted. Thoſe neuertheleſſe, that haue preſumed, or ſhall hereafter preſume ſo to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue
<pb facs="tcp:4347:21"/> and entertaine other mens Citizens and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, contrarie to the tenor of this our preſent De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree; If they doe not remit and ſend them away, within one moneth after the intimation of theſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents made vnto them, ſhall for euery time ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending, forfeit and pay one hundred markes, the one halfe into the Emperours Exchequer, and the other halfe to the Lords of thoſe that were ſo recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, without fauour or pardon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="proclamation">
               <head>Of Defiances.</head>
               <p>SVch men as pretend to haue iuſt cauſe of Defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance againſt any man, in thoſe places where they dwell not or commonly inhabit, and ſodainly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie them, we declare, ſuch dammages as ſhall hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen or ariſe, by burning, ſpoyling, or pillage of the parties defied, with their honour, be ſatisfied: And becauſe other mens fraud and deceit ſhould not be vpholden nor maintained. We ordayne this Law for euer to be kept and obſerued. That ſuch Defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances made, or that in time to come ſhall be made againſt any Lords, or perſons, with whom they are conuerſant, familiar and friends, ſhalbe of no force nor valew; neither ſhall it bee lawfull, vnder any pretence whatſoeuer, to defie any man, and to ſpoyle, burne, and bereaue him of his goods, &amp;c. vnleſſe ſuch defiance be certified, and made perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally vnto the party defied three dayes before, or elſe, in the place where he was wont to dwell, and that the party defying can teſtifie the ſame Defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
<pb facs="tcp:4347:21"/> to be ſo made, by lawfull witneſſes: And who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer ſhall doe the contrary, ſhall for the ſame, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre infamie and diſgrace, as if no defiance had beene made: whom we alſo cenſure by the Law to be puniſhed as a traitor: Wee likewiſe prohibit and condemne all warre, and uniuſt quarrells, &amp; eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vnlawfull burnings, ſpoylings, &amp; pillages, vndue and extraordinary toles, &amp; ſafe-conducts, and ſuch extraordinary exactions, as are vſed to be made and taken for ſuch ſafe-conducts, vpon the paines in the Lawes aforeſaid, and ſuch like, ordained and ſet downe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="proclamation">
               <head>A Letter of Certificate or warning, to be giuen to the Electors to aſſemble about the election of the King of <hi>Romaines.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ILluſtrious and magnanimous Prince <hi>H.</hi> Margraue of <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> High-Chamberlaine of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, Prince Elector, and our moſt eſpeciall friend; The election of the King of <hi>Romans,</hi> which for good cauſes is now to be made, we doe by theſe preſents certifie vnto you, and according to your office and dutie, call you to the Election aforeſaid, to the end that at ſuch a day, &amp;c. within three moneths, order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enſuing one the other, eyther you, or your depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, or deputies (ſufficiently authorized) may take care to be at the place for the ſame appoynted, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Law in the ſame caſe prouided, there to deliberate, conferre, and agree, with the other Princes our co-Electors, vpon the election of the ſaid King of <hi>Romaines</hi> (by Gods helpe) to be made Emperour, and there to ſtay and remaine, vntill
<pb facs="tcp:4347:22"/> the ſaid election be fully finiſhed and accompliſhed, and to doe and performe all other things thereunto appertaining, as by the Laws in that caſe prouided are ſet downe; wherein we pray you not to faile: otherwiſe, notwithſtanding yours, or your depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties abſence, wee will, (with the Princes your co-Electors and ours) (according to the authoritie in that caſe prouided by the Law) proceede to the Election.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="proclamation">
               <head>A forme of a Letter of Depulation to be made by one of the Princes Electors vnto his Deputie or Deputies, by him to be ſent to the Election.</head>
               <p>VVEe by the grace of God, &amp;c. of the holie Empire &amp;c. by theſe preſents make known vnto all men, That foraſmuch as the Election of the King of <hi>Romaines,</hi> for certaine ſpeciall cauſes is to be made; wee reſpecting the honour of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, and deſiring to further and aduance the ſame, leſt it ſhould be neglected or omitted, being aſſured of the fidelitie, induſtrie and circumſpection of our louing friend, or friends, &amp;c. and knowing by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dubitate preſumption, the ſingular confidence of them in generall, and of euery one of them in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular; ſo that without contrarietie, whatſoeuer one of them ſhall take in hand, the others will agree, conſent vnto, and performe<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> according to Law, and reaſon, in the beſt manner, meanes and forme that we may or can deuiſe, we haue made, elected and choſen them to be our lawfull Deputies, in any place where-ſoeuer, together with the other
<pb facs="tcp:4347:22"/> Princes our co-Electors, aſwel eccleſiaſticall as tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall, to agree and conſult vpon ſome fit perſon to be choſen King of <hi>Romaines,</hi> and for vs, and in our name, in the ſame conſultation to be made, to name a perſon, and the ſame to chooſe to be King of <hi>Romaines,</hi> and after to be Emperour: And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in our name to take any neceſſary due, and accuſtomed oathe in that behalfe vſed, or to be v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, as alſo to make and appoynt one or more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties in his or their places, and them againe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke at his or their willes and pleaſures; and to doe and performe all other things, which, in, or about the premiſes (vntill the ſaide conſultation, deliberation, and election be finiſhed and done) ſhal be neceſſary fit, and conuenient, as we, and in ſuch manner and forme, as we may, can, or might poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly doe, if we were perſonally preſent, at the ſayd conſultation, deliberation, nomination and election, holding, accounting and conferring, and by theſe preſents, for euer hereafter confirming, whatſoeuer our Deputies and Subſtitutes aforeſaid, as alſo their Deputies or Subſtitutes, or euery, or any of them in generall or particular ſhall do, act, and performe in the premiſes, in what manner ſoeuer, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="proclamation">
               <head>Of the order in Proceſsion to be holden by the Arch-bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, electors of the Empire.</head>
               <p>FOr that it is before ſet downe and declared in the beginning of theſe our Conſtitutions, what order ſhall bee helde and obſerued by the Eccleſiaſticall Princes Electors, in ſitting and placing themſelues
<pb facs="tcp:4347:23"/> in Counſell, at the Table, and other Solemnities im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall, where the Princes Electors are to goe with, ſit, or accompany the Emperour, or the King of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains,</hi> wherein we thinke to haue ſufficiently decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red what ſhall be done at thoſe times, and thoſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: We thinke it conuenient to declare what order ſhall be vſed by them, when the Emperour, or the King of <hi>Romaines</hi> ſhall goe abroad or in proceſſion; Therefore wee ordayne this perpetuall order to be obſerued, That as often, and when as the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour or King of <hi>Romaines,</hi> with the ſaid Princes Electors, is to goe on proceſſion; and that the Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner is to be borne before him, the Arch-biſhop of <hi>Tryer</hi> ſhall goe directly next before the Emperour, or the King, and he onely that beares the Banner, ſhall goe betweene them: And when the Emperor or King goes abroade without the Banner, then the ſaid Arch-biſhop ſhall goe in like manner directly before the Emperour or King, and no man ſhall goe betweene them; and the other two Arch-biſhops, Electors ſhall obſerue their places, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the diſtinction of their Prouinces, touching their ſitting in places aforeſaid, formerly declared, and ſo likewiſe to be obſerued in Proceſſions.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="proclamation">
               <head>Of the order in Proceſſion to be holden by the temporall Princes Electors, and by whom the enſignes of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour ſhall be borne.</head>
               <p>TO declare what order is to be vſed when the Emperour or King of <hi>Romaines</hi> goes in Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, by the ſecular Princes Electors (whereof
<pb facs="tcp:4347:23"/> wee haue formerly ſpoken,) We ordaine and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point, that as often as any celebration of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall aſſemblies is to be done, where the Princes E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectors are to accompany the Emperour or King of <hi>Romaines</hi> when he goeth abroad, or on proceſſion, and that the imperiall or regall enſignes are to be borne before them, the Duke of <hi>Saxon,</hi> bearing the imperiall or regall ſword, ſhall goe next before the Emperour or King, betweene the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Tryer</hi> and him; the Countie <hi>Palatine</hi> of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> ſhall beare the imperiall globe on the right hand; the Margraue of <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> the Scepter on the left hand, and the King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> ſhall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly goe next behinde the Emperour.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="proclamation">
               <head>Of the bleſsing to be giuen by the Arch-biſhops, in the Emperours preſence.</head>
               <p>AS often as in the Emperours or the King of <hi>Romaines</hi> preſence, Maſſe is to be celebrated, &amp; that the Arch-biſhops of <hi>Mentz, Tryer,</hi> and <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len,</hi> or two of them ſhall chance to be preſent, at the Confeſſion which is wont to be ſaid before Maſſe, and in reaching or offering the Goſpel to be kiſt, and the <hi>Pax</hi> after the <hi>Agnus Dei</hi> is borne about, as alſo in the <hi>Benediction,</hi> after the ſolemnitie of the Maſſe is finiſhed, and likewiſe before Maſſe is ſaid, and at grace after meate, this order ſhall be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued among them, which by their counſell and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe we haue ſet downe, that the firſt day all theſe things ſhall be obſerued and done by the firſt, the ſecond day by the ſecond, and the third day by the
<pb facs="tcp:4347:24"/> third of them, and in the abſence of the firſt, ſecond, or third of them, in that caſe the ſecond ſhall doe that which the firſt or the laſt ſhould haue done, and ſo orderly as it falles out when any of them is not preſent, that they may one after another or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly by courſe obtaine that honour, and giue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample vnto others to doe the like, when time ſhall fall out, and thereby incite them to the ſame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuence and charitable inclination, in obſeruing the ſame courſe. If any man ſhall enter into any wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed conſpiracie or faction, by oath or promiſe, with any Princes, Gentlemen, or priuate and common people, or ſhall giue them any counſell or aduiſe to kill the reuerent and illuſtrious Princes Electors, eccleſiaſticall or temporall, or any of them, for they are a part or our body, he or they, that in ſuch caſe are found guilty, ſhall be puniſhed for the ſame fact of conſpiracie, as if they had really committed the fact, and were guilty of high-treaſon, by loſſe of their liues, and forfeiture of all their Lands and Goods to the Emperour, and his or their ſonnes, whoſe life, (by our ſpeciall imperiall fauour) wee ſpare, ſhall be puniſhed, for his fathers fault, hee ſhall looſe his fathers inheritance, and others ſhall enioy the ſame; he ſhall be incapable of making a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny will, or of receiuing any thing by another mans will, he ſhall alwaies be needy and poore, his fathers infamie ſhall euer be imputed vnto him, he ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be admitted into any honour, nor his oath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to be good; and to conclude, hee ſhall be ſo miſerable, and in perpetuall pouerty, that death to him ſhall be a comfort, and life a puniſhment.
<pb facs="tcp:4347:24"/> And further, we command him ſo to be noted &amp; ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, that without our ſpeciall licenſe, hee ſhall not at any time preſume or be permitted to haue acceſſe vnto our perſon: Touching the daughters, how many ſoeuer they be, they ſhall not haue the full fourth part of their Mothers goods; whether ſhe die inteſtate or not, wee will take order, that they ſhall haue an indifferent part thereof for their reliefe, rather then the whol<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as if they were her heires; for their ſentence in truth, ought not to be ſo rigorous, that by infirmitie of ſexe are of leſſe power to commit euill. Emancipations or Feoff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments made by the parents, either to the ſonnes or daughters, ſhall be voyde and of none effect, neither ſhal any fraudulent alienations, made by the ſaid pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, from the time that they once entred into the ſaid conſpiracies and factions, be good nor allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in law: And touching their wiues dowries, if they were ſo made by their huſbands vnto them that the reuerſion thereof ſhould reuert vnto the ſonnes, after the wiues deceaſe, they ſhall acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that reuerſion to reuert vnto our Exchequer, the fourth part whereof ought rather to fall vnto the daughters then to the ſonnes; and that puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which we ſet downe and appoint, for the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and their ſonnes, the ſame ſeuerity alſo ſhall be vſed towards the Seruants, Officers and Abetters of them, and of their ſonnes. But if any of them, that in the beginning and entrance into the ſaid faction, ſhall ſeeme to keepe counſell with the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties guilty, and afterward ſhall diſcloſe it, and rather ſeeke to croſſe it for our good and honour, and they
<pb facs="tcp:4347:25"/> alſo that ſhall haue ſought to put their malitious faction in practiſe, if at laſt, vnknowne to the other conſpirators, they ſhall ſecretly diſcloſe it, wee iudge them to be worthy of pardon and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe. We further ordaine, that if any conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, ſhall haue beene made againſt the ſaid Princes Electors, ſpirituall or temporall, by any man that is dead, and the ſame after his death is knowne and diſcouered, that crime concerning the hurt and danger of the life of the Princes Electors, touching the imperiall maieſtie, for if the members be hurt, the head cannot be well, nor in ſafetie, therefore wee will and commaund, that after the death of the partie that is knowne to haue beene guilty in his life time, the ſame fault ſhall be puniſhed, that the dead partie being found guilty, his memorie may be extinguiſhed, and his goods taken away from his ſucceſſours; for if any man conceiueth or imagineth miſchiefe, if followeth thereby that his minde was depraued; and therefore ſeeing that he did imagine and inuent ſuch a miſchiefe, he had no power to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lienate nor infranchiſe the ſame, nor yet by right in this caſe to take order for the payment of his debts. Therefore if the members be hurt, the head muſt needes be the worſe, that is, if any conſpiracie were made againſt the Princes Electors, ſpirituall or temporall, by any man that is dead, the goods and lands of the ſaid perſon ſhall be attached, as if hee had beene executed for the ſame offence.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="proclamation">
               <pb facs="tcp:4347:25"/>
               <head>Touching the integritie that is to be obſerued among the Princes Electors.</head>
               <p>IF other Princes of our Empire doe agree in vnitie of ſpirit and willes to obſerue iuſtice and equitie, that the Subiects of the Empire may thereby liue in peace and tranquilitie; much more ought the Princes Electors of the Empire to ſeeke to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and preſerue the ſame; for where the danger is moſt euident, there it ought more ſpeedily to be preuented, left thoſe the pillars breaking, the whole houſe ſhould fall to decay. Therefore We decree and ordaine this to be a perpetuall Law, That as in former time, out of the memory of man, ſo in time to come, the illuſtrious and magnificent Princes, the King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> the Earle <hi>Palatine</hi> of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Saxon,</hi> and the Margraue of <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> being ſtrictly bound together by their Territories, ought not touching homages, vaſſalage, and other rights to them belonging, to be ſeperated, diuided, or in any wiſe diſmembred, but to the end that they may rather be, and remaine in their perfect integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, their eldeſt ſonne, ſhall ſucceed them in their rights, priuiledges and dominions; vnleſſe hee ſhall chance to be diſtract of his ſences, fooliſh, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe defectiue in mind, for the which cauſe he ought not, nor cannot gouerne others; in which caſes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing prohibited of ſucceſſion therein, the ſecond ſon (if there be any) or ſome other elder brother or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin, that is a Temporall Prince, and next of bloud, that lineally deſcendeth from the father, ſhall be his ſucceſſor, who then ſhal deale kindly with the other
<pb facs="tcp:4347:26"/> brethren and ſiſters, touching their maintenance, and as hee ſhall thinke good, and according to his meanes, without diuiding or diſmembring the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipality and appurtenances thereof in any ſort.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="proclamation">
               <head>Touching the Emperours Court and Seſsions.</head>
               <p>THat day whereon the Emperours or the King of <hi>Romaines</hi> Court is to be holden, at an houre appointed, the Princes Electors both Spirituall and Temporall, ſhall come to the Emperours, or Kings Pallace, and there the Emperour or the King ſhall put on all his Imperiall Roabes, and mounting vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their horſes, all of them ſhall goe with the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, or the King, to the place where the Court is to be holden, orderly, and in manner and forme (as it is formerly ſet downe in our Decree, to that end made;) The chiefe Chancellour, in whoſe precinct or iuriſdiction it ſhall happen to be, ſhall beare or carry all the Seales and imperiall and regall Tipes vpon a ſiluer wand: The Secular Princes Electors, ſhall beare the Scepter, the Ball, the Sword, euery one as he is orderly to doe it, according to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree for the ſame purpoſe made; They ſhall likewiſe beare, (going directly next before, the Arch-biſhop of <hi>Tryer,</hi> keeping his ordinary place) firſt the Crown of <hi>Aquſgranie,</hi> then the Crowne of <hi>Millaine,</hi> before the Emperour, as then apparelled in his Imperiall Roabes, which ſhall bee borne by other inferiour Princes, thereunto appointed by the Emperour. The Empreſſe or the Queene of <hi>Romaines</hi> apparel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in her Imperiall veſtures, ſhall goe and follow after the Emperour or the King of <hi>Romaines,</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:4347:26"/> the King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> (whoſe place is to goe next af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Emperour) an indifferent ſpace from them; her Ladies and Maides of Honor orderly following her to the Court.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="proclamation">
               <head>The offices of the Princes Electors at the Solemnities which are to be obſerued in the Emperours Court at royall feaſts and aſſemblies.</head>
               <p>VVE ordaine and appoint, that when the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour or King of <hi>Romaines</hi> ſhall celebrate any ſolemne feaſts, whereat the Princes Electors are to ſerue, and execute their Offices heereafter declared and ſet downe; the Emperour or the King ſitting in the Imperiall Throne, the Duke of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xon</hi> ſhall execute his office in this manner: Before the Gate of the Emperour, or the King, there ſhall be ſet a heape of Oates, ſo high that it ſhall reach to the breaſt or ſaddle of the horſe, whereon the ſayd Duke ſhall ride, who ſhall beare in his hand a ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer Wand, and a Meaſure of ſiluer, which both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether ſhall weigh two hundred Markes of ſiluer; and ſitting vpon his horſe, ſhall firſt fill that mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure full of Oates, and ſhall giue it to his ſeruant that is next vnto him; which done, ſticking his ſtaffe in the Oates, hee ſhall goe backe againe; and then his vice-Marſhall, <hi>Seigneur de Papenheym,</hi> comming thither, or in his abſence, the Marſhall of the Court, ſhall diſtribute the reſt of the Oates. The Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour or the King being gone in to ſit at the Table, the Arch-biſhops, Princes Electors, ſtanding before the Table, with the reſt of the Prelates, ſhall ſay grace, according to the order formerly ſet downe:
<pb facs="tcp:4347:27"/> and when grace is ſayd, the three Arch-biſhops (if they be all there) or two, or one of them, ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the Imperiall or Regall Seale and Tipe from the Chancellor of the Court, hee in whoſe Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellours iuriſdiction that feaſt or ſolemnitie ſhall chaunce to be celebrated, ſtanding in the middle, and the other two on either ſide of him, ſhall all lay their hands vpon the Staffe, whereon the ſaid Seale and Type hangs, and ſo carry it, and with great reuerence laye it vpon the Table before the Emperour, or the King, who preſently ſhall deliuer the ſame againe vnto them, &amp; in whoſe Arch-chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celors precinct it ſhall then be, as aforeſaid, he ſhall carry the greater Seale about his necke, to the end of the Table, and from thence to his houſe, riding from the Emperours Court vpon his horſe.</p>
               <p>The Staffe whereof mention was formerly made, muſt be ſiluer, waighing two hundred Markes, the third part of the value whereof euery one of the Arch-Biſhops muſt pay and contribute equally, and that Staffe with the Seales and Types, muſt preſently be giuen to the Chancelour of the Emperours Court, to vſe them when occaſion ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth; &amp; after that he who by order carrying the great Seale about his necke from the Court, is gone home to his lodging, as aforeſaid, he ſhall preſently ſend it backe againe by one of his friends on horſe-backe to the Emperours Court, to the Chancelour, which according to the dignitie of the place, and the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour which hee is to beare to the Court of the Chancerie, hee is bound freely to deliuer to the ſaid Chancelour. Then the Margraue of <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4347:27"/> Lord High-Chamberlaine of the Empire, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming on horſe-backe with a Siluer Baſon (waying twelue Markes in Siluer,) full of water in his hand, and a fine cleane Towell on his arme, lighting downe, muſt giue the Emperour or King of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines</hi> water to waſh his hands; after him the Earle <hi>Palatine</hi> of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> muſt come on horſe-backe with foure ſiluer Platters in his hands full of meate, euery one of them waying three Markes in value, who lighting off from his horſe, muſt carrie and ſet them downe vpon the Table before the Emperour, or King; after him the King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> chiefe But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of the Empire, riding on a horſe, with a Nap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kin on his arme, and a couered cup in his hand, (waighing twelue Markes) full of Wine mixt with water, lighting downe, giueth the cup to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour or King of <hi>Romaines,</hi> to drinke. Further, wee ordaine, that the Secular Princes, Electors, hauing performed their offices, the Earle of <hi>Falkenſtein,</hi> vice-Chamberlaine, ſhall take the Horſe and Baſon from the Margraue of <hi>Brandenburgh</hi> for his fee; the chiefe maſter cooke of <hi>Noremburgh,</hi> the horſe and diſhes from the Earle <hi>Palatine</hi> for his fee; the Earle of <hi>Lim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh</hi> vice-Butler, the Horſe and Cup from the King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> for his fee; and the Baron of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penheym,</hi> vice-Marſhall, the Horſe, Staffe, and Meaſure aforeſaid, from the Duke of <hi>Saxon</hi> for his fee, if they be there perſonally preſent, to execute their offices; but if they or any of them ſhall be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at that time, then the ordinary officers of the Emperours or King of <hi>Romaines</hi> Court, in their abſence, that is to ſay, in euery one of their pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb facs="tcp:4347:28"/> that are abſent, whoſe place is to execute the ſame, as to his office belongeth, ſhall take away and haue the aforeſaid things. The Emperors table muſt be in ſuth ſort prepared &amp; placed, that it muſt ſtand ſix foot higher then the reſt of the tables in the hall, whereat (vpon that day) the Emperour or King of <hi>Romaines</hi> muſt ſit alone. The Table whereat the Empreſſe or Queene of <hi>Romaines</hi> ſhall ſit, muſt ſtand on the one ſide of the Hall, three foote lower then the Emperours Table, and ſo many foot high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, aboue the Princes Electors, which Princes ſhall haue, their Seates or Tables, one as high as another, lower then the Emperours or Kings Table, being ſeauen in number, which ſhall ſtand, three on the right hand, and three on the left, and the ſeauenth directly before the Emperour, or King, (as in our Ordinance formerly made for the order &amp; manner by them to be obſerued in ſitting downe in the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours preſence, is at large declared) and no man ſhall ſit with them at the ſaide Tables, but them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues alone: Neyther ſhall any of the ſaide ſecular Princes Electors, hauing performed his office, ſit downe at the Table appoynted for him, as long as the reſt of his Co-electors, Princes, are performing their offices; but while any of them, or their Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, are about the performing therof, he ſhal ſtand at the Table appointed for him, expecting the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of their offices aforeſaid, and then euerie one of them ſhall ſit downe at his ſeuerall Table.</p>
               <p>Alſo, we finde in the ancient Records, time out of minde, that thoſe that were our Predeceſſors thought it fit and conuenient to be obſerued, that
<pb facs="tcp:4347:28"/> the election of the King of <hi>Romaines,</hi> to be future Emperour, ſhould be made in the City of <hi>Franc<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> and that his firſt Coronation ſhould bee done in the City of <hi>Aquiſgranie,</hi> and the firſt ſolemne feaſt held in the City of <hi>Noremburgh:</hi> wherefore, for many conſiderations, we ordaine and appoynt the ſame to be ſo obſerued in time to come, vnleſſe any lawfull cauſe of hinderance or impeachment there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of fall out to the contrary. And if that any of the Princes Electors Spirituall or Temporall, vpon iuſt and good occaſion; being ſummoned to be there at the ſayd feaſt, cannot come, he ſhall ſend his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putie; but of what eſtate or dignitie ſoeuer hee be that is ſo ſent for his deputy, yet hee ſhall not ſit downe at the Table, or in the ſeate of him that ſent him. Further, theſe offices and other things being performed at the ſayde Imperiall or Kingly feaſt: The maſter or Steward of the feaſt ſhall haue all the tables, boords and ſcaffolds of wood for his fee, that was prepared againſt that feaſt for the Emperour and the King, as alſo for the Electors, at the cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration thereof, according to ancient cuſtome.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="proclamation">
               <head>What Fees the Officers are to haue when the Princes acknowledge Fealtie to the Emperour or King of Romaines.</head>
               <p>WE ordaine this Imperiall Decree, that the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces Electors, Spirituall and Temporall, when they acknowledge their fealty to the Emperour or the King of <hi>Romaines,</hi> ſhall not be bound to giue or pay any mony to any man, at that time, for that the
<pb facs="tcp:4347:29"/> mony which is due to Officers in that kinde, ſeeing the ſayd Princes Electors, are euery one ſuperior Imperiall officers, and haue their Deputies or Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutes in euery one of their offices, giuen them by the <hi>Romaine</hi> Princes; it were abſurd, that vnder-Officers or Subſtitutes ſhould, vpon any colour whatſoeuer, aske or exact any fees of their Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors, vnleſſe the ſaide Princes of their owne free wills and liberalities, will giue them any thing. But other Princes, both Eccleſiaſtical and Secular, when they (as aforeſayd) acknowledge fealty vnto the Emperour of <hi>Rome,</hi> or to the King, they ſhall giue to the Kings or the Emperors officers of the Court, ſixty and ſix markes of ſiluer, vnleſſe any of them can by ſpeciall priuiledge or indulgence, by the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours formerly granted to them, diſcharge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues thereof, and proue, that they are free from paying ſuch, or any the like fees, vſed when they acknowledged their fealties; which ſayd ſixty ſixe markes, the Maſter or Steward of the ſaid Imperiall feaſt, ſhall diuide in this manner. Firſt, reſeruing ten markes for himſelfe, hee ſhall giue, to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors or Kings Chancelor of the court, ten marks, to the Maſters of the Court, Clarks, and Doctors, three markes, and to the Clarke of the Seale, for Wax and Parchment, one marke; in ſuch manner neuertheleſſe, that the Chancellor and Clarkes ſhall not take ſuch fees of the Princes, but onely to te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie that they haue done their fealty, and to ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the ſame. The ſaid Maſter alſo ſhall giue vnto the vice-Butler of <hi>Limburgh,</hi> ten markes, to the maſter Cooke of <hi>Noremburgh,</hi> ten markes, to the
<pb facs="tcp:4347:29"/> vice-Marſhall of <hi>Papenheim,</hi> ten markes, and to the vice-Chamberlaine of <hi>Falkenstein,</hi> ten markes; vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this condition neuertheleſſe, if they, and euery of them ſhall be preſent at the Court, to execute their offices according to their places; and that if they, or any of them be abſent, then the Officers of the Imperiall or Kings Court, that vſe to ſerue in thoſe Offices, ſhall ſupply their ſayd places, euery one as it falls out, and ſhall haue the ſaid fees accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly. And when any Prince ſitting vpon an horſe or other beaſt, doth his fealty to the Emperour or the King, that horſe or beaſt, of what kinde ſoeuer it be, belongeth as a fee vnto the chiefe Marſhall, the Duke of <hi>Saxon,</hi> if he be preſent, or elſe, to the vice-Marſhall of <hi>Papenheim;</hi> and in his abſence to the Marſhall of the Emperours or Kings Court.</p>
               <p>Foraſmuch as that for the honour of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine</hi> Emperour, it is expedient, that the ſaide Emperour hauing to deale and treate with diuers Nations, of ſundry and ſeuerall Languages, ſhould vnderſtand and ſpeake the ſaid Languages: It is fit and conuenient in euery mans iudgement, that the Princes Electors, being the pillers and ſupporters of the Empire, ſhould be inſtructed and taught di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers Languages, that they may vnderſtand euery man, and be vnderſtood of them; and thereby aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting the Emperour in his principall and ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt affaires, he may the more be honoured. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee ordayne and appoint, that the illuſtrious Princes Electors, <hi>viz.</hi> the King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> the County <hi>Palatine</hi> of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Saxon,</hi> and the Margraue of <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> their ſonnes,
<pb facs="tcp:4347:30"/> heires, and ſucceſſors, when they can perfectly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand and ſpeake their owne mother Language, the High-<hi>Germaine</hi> tongues, at the age of ſeauen yeares they ſhall be taught to ſpeake the <hi>Latin, Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian,</hi> and <hi>Slauonian</hi> tongues, ſo that at foureteene yeares of age, by the helpe of God, they may well vnderſtand the ſame, being not onely neceſſary, but for ſpeciall cauſes moſt neceſſarie, for that thoſe Languages are much vſed in the Empire, and by them they may the eaſſier mannage the Imperiall affaires: Which, the better to effect, we thinke it fit and conuenient, that the Fathers ſhould leaue the charge of their ſonnes, if they haue any, or of their next kinſmen, whom they know muſt and ſhall be their heires and ſucceſſors in their honours and lands, and eyther ſend them to ſuch places where they may be inſtructed and taught thoſe lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, or elſe keepe ſuch Maiſters and Inſtructers for them in their houſes, together with yong Boyes that are skilfull in thoſe Languages, to beare them company, that they may (by thoſe meanes) the readilier, ſooner and perfectlier learne, and be inſtructed in the ſame. (<g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g>)</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:4347:30"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
